Today I want to talk about
what to me is a very interesting
topic, and that is futures markets.
Not very interesting to most people.
Most people have no idea what they are.
But I think that futures markets, what we're really
talking about is, there's different ways of viewing it.
Futures markets for things like agricultural commodities, or
interest rates, or financial securities are markets about
the future.
They're markets that, in some sense, predict the future.
And future matters, right?
We live a life.
We have a long horizon.
And we have to be careful.
We have to be careful.
I said before, I think,
that your planning horizon must be
at least a century.
Right?
Because you probably live that long anyway with modern
medicine, and you care about other people, too.
So, the beauty of futures
markets is that we have prices
for the future.
We talked already about forward markets, and we talked
about forward interest rates.
And that is a very interesting topic.
And I think that's a very interesting topic.
And I think that is
related to what we're talking about.
Forwards and futures are similar concepts.
Futures is the more precise concept, or the more developed
concept.
And I'll explain the
difference between forwards and futures.
But just in a nutshell,
futures markets are organized markets,
like the stock market, that trade standardized contracts,
representing things that will happen at future dates.
And because they're standardized, they're worldwide.
Everybody looks at them and uses them.
Whereas forward markets are
more specialized markets that typically
are not as easy to interpret or as clear.
And they're not as easy to interpret or as clear.
So, futures markets are, in
some sense, more fundamental and important.
I have a particular interest.
I've been interested in futures
markets myself for many years.
And wondering why they're not
even bigger and more important.
So, in 1993, I wrote
a book called Macro Markets about,
let's make our markets bigger
and more important and more pervasive.
And I've been trying to do that.
Notably, in 2006, I was
working with the Chicago Mercantile Exchange,
which is the biggest futures market in the world.
And we created Home Price Futures.
And they've been trading now for five years.
But I'm not really going to talk
about them, because they have so far disappointed.
They're not important, at least not yet.
But I'm going to talk about some important futures markets.
And I'm going to talk about
some of the most important futures markets.
So, let me, first, I want to put
a, okay, just a couple of definitions up.
Futures, that's what we're going to
talk about most in this lecture.
And it has a special meaning in finance.
And I was contrasting that to four words.
And I'm going to talk about the two.
And so, but both of these together are derivatives.
And that means that they, the price in these
markets derives from a price in some other market.
There's a primary or secondary market.
There's a primary or underlying
market, which has its own price.
And then there's a derivative market that
has a futures price or a forward price.
I guess I'm speaking in kind of abstract terms.
So, let me just start.
I haven't really, I want to give you an example.
And we'll see better what I'm talking about.
But let me just first
comment just on this word, derivatives.
To people in finance, derivatives are
an exciting development of financial markets.
We start out with a simple market and we
develop derivative markets that add more detail and information
than was in the underlying or primary market.
That's exciting.
I find it exciting.
However, I don't know if you,
how often you hear this word derivatives.
It's become a four-letter word.
It's become an ugly word.
Why is that?
I think it's because people blame the current
financial crisis on derivatives, whether rightly or wrongly.
And it's because I think there's a public anger.
There's a public anger about derivatives
that is largely due to misunderstanding.
I mentioned before that I think
that finance tends to attract sociopaths.
I mentioned, I defined that for you.
People who want to manipulate and fool and deceive people.
But I don't think the financial
community is particularly populated by sociopaths.
You might think so, reading some accounts.
But I think it's not true.
And I think it's not true because the financial
community knows about this problem and ejects such people.
They get caught and you can't make
a career in finance if you're a sociopath.
So, if you think you have this problem, that you have
sociopathic tendencies, I would advise you not to go into finance.
Because you will get caught.
Because you will get caught and ejected.
So, save yourself the trouble.
Don't go into finance.
Pick some field where you can't hurt anybody.
That would be a smart thing to
do, if you have such a problem.
So, I think we need to regulate derivatives markets.
And that's what I'm talking about.
And we need self-regulation of the markets themselves.
But we need government regulation as well.
But there's nothing evil about derivatives.
And in fact, derivatives are fundamental to
the way I think a modern economy works.
So, I had you read an article, I put it
on an earlier section of the reading list, by Charles Conant.
Who wrote a book in 1904
called Wall Street and the Capital.
And I don't know if you,
you should have read that by now.
But he starts out by saying, it's just
amazing how public opinion thinks that speculation is evil.
And they don't understand that speculation is just business.
I mean, business decisions involve guesses about the future.
And so, when you have well-developed
markets, these guesses become market prices.
And so, the prices go
into the calculations that everyone makes.
And the calculations are just done better.
Somehow, there's just a failure
for most people to understand it.
And I'm hoping in this lecture to try
to give some more understanding of these markets.
I'm not sure.
But I think they're fascinating.
Most people apparently don't.
Because you don't hear them brought up very much.
I wanted to just say a little bit more about
hostility toward derivative markets and futures markets and speculation in general.
In 1991, that was 20 years ago, I wrote a
joint paper with a, I don't remember whether I mentioned this.
Probably not.
With a Russian, a young man from Russia that
I met when I was visiting the Soviet Union.
Just before the end of the Soviet Union.
And we were talking about
how antagonistic Russians are toward capitalism.
And he said, this is a big problem.
Russia just can't embrace capitalism.
People hate it.
They hate the profit makers and the financiers.
And I said to him, well, you know.
It's the same in the U.S.
How do you know it's any worse in Russia?
And so, we decided to do a questionnaire survey.
And I was going to read one of the questions.
Comparing people in Moscow and people in New York.
To see which one understands capitalism better.
So, one of the questions
that we had was the following.
We wrote these questions and translated them into Russian.
And we tried to make them exactly
the same question between Russian and English.
All right.
Here's the question we asked in both cities.
Grain traders in capitalist countries
sometimes hold grain without selling it.
Putting it in temporary storage
in anticipation of higher prices later.
Do you think this speculation will cause more
frequent shortages of flour, bread and other grain products?
Or will it cause such shortages to become rarer?
What do you think people said?
Does the process of speculating in
grain cause problems or solve problems?
Well, we found that in the U.S.A.
66% said it will make shortages more common.
But in the Soviet Union, in Moscow, only
45% thought it would make shortages more common.
Both of them were wrong.
A lot of them were wrong.
But the Russians were better.
The Russians were better, closer
to the truth than the Americans.
Here, living in the financial capital of the U.S.A.,
most people think that speculating in grain creates problems.
But wait a minute.
What is speculation in grain?
That means holding it off
for expecting higher prices later, right?
Isn't that what you have to do
if you are managing a grain market?
Now, think of it this way.
And I'm coming now to agricultural future.
In the most world, there is
one harvest of wheat every year, okay?
And that harvest comes in a certain time
of the year, every year, once a year.
And it has to be held
in storage over the year, right?
Because people don't eat it all at once.
You eat it over the whole year.
So, somebody is storing grain.
This is a fundamental problem, okay?
That's a business.
And you have to know that somewhere, there is some warehouse
holding the grain that you will be consuming in six months' time.
And that warehouse is run
by some professionals who do that.
And if they think prices are higher later,
they will keep it longer in the warehouse.
And what does that do?
That evens out the price.
It doesn't make it worse.
If they think there is going to be a shortage of grain,
they hold it back now and the price of grain goes up.
And so, everyone starts consuming a
little less because of the higher price.
And it smooths things out and it works better.
This is elementary economics, but it's
not understood, I think, by most people.
And the futures markets are just
sophisticated markets that help that process.
So, I'm going to start with
agricultural futures in talking about this.
And I want to start
also with a very important point.
I'm going to start with agriculture.
And I want to start with a very
elementary example because it's the first futures market.
So, where do you think futures markets started?
Anyone have a – you would think
it started in New York or Chicago, right?
Or London, right?
Or Paris.
It actually started in Japan in a place
called Dojima, which is in the city of Osaka.
And they started in the –
I think it was the early 1600s.
And so, let's just go back, if we can
go back to the year 1673 in Osaka, Japan.
Japan was heavily dependent on rice, okay?
And the rice farmers would farm all over
Japan, but there was a rice market in Dojima,
which was the national rice market.
And I have data here, according to a study,
there were 91 rice warehouses in Dojima in 1673.
That's a long time ago, isn't it?
So, it was a big storage place for rice.
And they were storing it all year.
And people would come, people who were
merchants for rice, they would come to Dojima,
and they would sign contracts to get rice.
I mean, I live in
some town 20 miles from here.
I'm a rice merchant.
I need a regular supply of rice from your warehouse.
Can you supply it to me?
And the guy would give you terms.
And that would be a forward contract, okay?
And this is what was happening before the futures market.
Forward contracts precede futures contracts, okay?
So, do you see what it is?
You're a rice merchant, you make a deal, you
sign a contract that I will pay you so much,
in currency, every month.
And you'll give me so much rice, and you'll deliver it
here, and I'll take it, and I'll sell it in my town.
Problems developed in the forward market that
led to the development of a futures market.
And the problem is, I'll tell you, one
of the problems is, is that there's counterparty risk.
You are a rice merchant.
You make a deal with a warehouse.
You have a contract.
That's one person dealing with one person, right?
What if one of the guys reneges on the deal?
So, for example, what if the price of rice falls?
Then you, the merchant, will say, I'm not going
to go back and buy according to this contract,
because it's cheaper now, right?
I'll buy it somewhere else.
So, I just don't show up.
And then the warehouse is
saying, what happened to our contract?
And you're nowhere to be found, okay?
So, you're not going to be found.
Or if it goes the other way, if
the price goes up, the warehouse might renege, right?
They'd say, you know, we signed this contract, but there's
something wrong with it, and we're not going to honor it.
So, it messes up.
It is also possible that one of the two counterparties is just
a sociopath or something, or is an alcoholic, or something is wrong.
So, the market doesn't work well.
So, what they invented in Japan
was the first true futures market.
And the market worked like this.
There was a trading floor in Dojima, and rice traders
would come there, and there were certain hours of the day
when you would trade contracts for future delivery.
But they were standardized contracts, mediated by the exchange,
so that there would be no problem with the contract.
And then every day, there would be a trading time.
And you could buy and sell contracts for future delivery.
Moreover, they enforced trading hours.
And this is something that's
kind of an interesting invention.
They didn't have, I guess they didn't
have clocks, I don't know what they had.
But they had a certain time when trading would stop, and
they wanted to stop all the trading at the same time.
They didn't want people dribbling out.
They wanted it to be a good market.
So, they would like to trade.
And they would light a burning fuse.
They would light a fuse.
And it would be a bright light
in the middle of the trading floor.
And you'd see the fuse burning down.
And when it burned out, all trading stopped.
So, they had trading hours.
Moreover, they had a problem that
some of the traders wouldn't stop trading.
So, this is something that they did in Dojima.
They had men called water men,
who came out with buckets of water.
And they would throw the buckets of
water on anyone who was still trading.
So, that worked.
It stopped trading.
They also had hand signals.
It got so, this was big.
This was big time.
You were trading rice for all of Japan.
And you may think the 1600s or 1700s are
long ago, but a lot of rice was traded.
And it got really noisy and difficult.
They found that it was, so many people were
trading on the floor that you couldn't hear anyone talk.
And there would be shouting and noisy.
And so, they devised a system of hand signals.
And the Dojima hand signals were, I
don't know exactly, but something like this.
If your hand was out, you
put your hand out, that means sell.
Put your hand this way, it meant buy.
And if you put three fingers
up, it means selling three contracts.
That kind of thing.
I don't know the whole system.
But that's where it started.
That whole concept was copied all
over the world in subsequent centuries.
So, what is it that happened?
Now, the other thing.
What were the contracts that you bought and sold?
The problem with the forward market
is that the contracts are all different.
One guy made a contract with one guy.
And he said, I want my delivery here.
And I don't like this kind of rice.
I want this kind.
Better make sure that there's not a single insect
in it, or I'm going to reject the whole thing.
But that's all different.
So, you don't know what these contracts.
You don't even know what the price of rice is.
If someone said, I paid so much to get rice.
But you have to say, well, under what circumstances?
And what kind of rice?
And where?
And what are the terms for possible failure?
There's so many terms in the contract.
So, you don't even know
what the price of rice is.
But at the futures market, they standardize the contract.
So, it may not be exactly what you want.
But it's standardized.
So, you deliver rice.
Now, I don't know all the details of Dojima.
But I'm talking about futures markets as they evolve.
In a modern futures market, agricultural futures market, you deliver your, the contract is to deliver some commodity,
like rice, at a specified future date, at a specified future warehouse, which would be run by the exchange.
And there's inspectors at the
warehouse who are expert on grain.
And they give, they verify, because they know rice.
They know it really well.
And they know that some rice has bugs in it.
They know how to find out.
They have a standard.
Of course, there can always
be some bugs in it, right?
But they have a standard and
they have a way of measuring.
And they get it right.
And so, all those contracts are exactly the same.
And so, they become, they become more and more important.
And they become more and more important.
And, of course, when you do these
things, you don't just get the price.
It turns out, funny thing, the futures market
almost becomes the real market, because they're all standardized.
The futures price, you know where it's delivered.
You know what's delivered exactly.
And so, people start to, the futures
market becomes the market, in a sense.
The fact that it's in the
future is, in a fact, a help.
It's well defined, whereas the
spot market is the market for
rice, or whatever it is, today, as it's traded.
The spot market is inscrutable.
It's hard to understand.
So, let's think about a farmer
today who grows rice, or wheat,
or soybeans, or something.
If you drive through farming countries, listen to the
radio, regularly they'll give prices.
Soybeans, wheat, rice, et cetera.
Why do they give that?
Because farmers care.
They're raising this stuff.
It's their whole livelihood.
Whether they make a profit or not depends on it.
What prices do they quote?
They quote the futures prices.
Even though they're in the future, but they've quoted them
because they mean something, and they're standardized.
So, that's why the futures market becomes the
central market.
I wanted to just say something about futures.
Japan started futures markets in the 1600s.
And
they were the world leader in rice futures until 1939.
And then, at World War
II, the Japanese government shut the
futures market down.
And to this day, since, there
is no rice futures market in
Japan, believe it or not.
The inventors.
They're talking now of starting it up again.
Where do they trade rice futures?
Well, it's the USA is the main market.
Even though you don't think
of the U.S. as a market.
You think of it as a market for rice.
But the point is that markets have to be centralized.
And people want the centralized market.
And if it happens to
be in Chicago, so be it.
So, it becomes a huge international rice market.
And so, I looked up,
this is called Rough Rice Futures.
And this is the futures curve as of last Friday.
So, what we have is different delivery months.
So, this is the future.
This is May of this year.
And then, there's other delivery months.
And then, there's next year.
It goes out about a year.
Different delivery dates.
And this is cents per 100 weight.
100 weight is 100 pounds of rice.
And since this is USA, we
mean 100 U.S. pounds of rice.
But anyone in the world can
figure this out and trade in
this market.
It's in dollars, because it's,
well, we're trading in the USA.
So, someone in Japan.
So, someone in Japan who
wants to trade in the futures
market has to come to the
USA, change their yen into dollars,
and do this.
Now, you see that the futures price is going up.
This was all quoted last Friday.
This is the market, essentially, right now.
But you see, it's a futures market, because it's giving
prices of rice at dates in the future.
These prices way out here
next year are not so reliable,
because there's not much trade.
The trade tends to dominate at the front month.
So, here's where most of the trade is.
They're trading May, and maybe this is July.
I forget exactly.
Is it clear what this means?
It's going up.
And it's going up pretty fast, isn't it?
From about less than 13 cents to 15 cents.
And it's going up.
It's going up.
It's going up to 15 cents.
What this means is that, in effect, the market is
expecting huge increases in the price of rice.
All right?
So, that's interesting.
Anyone who is doing business in
rice looks at this and says,
look, there's price increases anticipated.
Now, I just want to talk
about the world at this point in
history, and try to interpret this curve right.
You must have heard that there is a few
things that are happening.
There's a food shortage in the world developing.
And it's a source of crisis.
It's developing in the Middle East.
One reason why that's been given for the revolutions that
have happened in the Middle
East are that people are hungry.
There's dissatisfaction when the price of food goes up.
A lot of people are
living much more at the margin
than you'd imagine.
So, this increase in rice prices matters a lot.
And it's very interesting that it's showing this steep
increase in the price of rice.
Now, but the first thing you
want to think of as a
financier is, how much is this going up?
I didn't actually do the calculation.
If it goes up from 13.75
to 15.5, that's quite an increase
in six months, right?
So, it sounds like there's a profit opportunity here, right?
Buy rice today and sell it on the future.
I'm not going to sell it on the futures market.
Sell it in, this is
a good time to sell it.
I'll sell it in 2012.
And that's my futures profit.
I can lock in this
price today, because that's what the
futures market does.
The contract is a contract to
deliver rice as of that future
date.
And this would be in Chicago, OK?
And so, I could make a profit.
There must be something.
And that's why I said,
this is a very professional market
with real expertise.
You talk to the rice traders
or the wheat traders, they know
what they're doing.
Believe me, they know what they're doing.
We're looking at this for the first time.
It's people who trade this all their lives.
And if you ask, why is
it, look how much it's going up.
This is a big profit opportunity.
They'll tell you why it isn't.
Why it isn't such an opportunity as you think.
Why I can't make huge
money by trading in rice, because
otherwise other people would do it.
This is such a liquid
market, open to everybody in the
world, so somebody's going to take advantage of this.
First of all, you understand, this is futures prices quoted
as of a single date for various horizons in the
future, don't get confused by it.
This is not a plot through time.
This is now.
This is what's quoted now.
And so, when you have an upward sloping futures curve
like that, we call that contango.
And that is what we usually see.
Maybe not upward sloping so much as this.
The opposite is called backwardation.
If futures prices are declining through time, that
happens, and I'll show you that
in a minute, but it's not
happening.
It's happening in rice.
So, not happening now in rice.
It must be that there is something that prevents you
from just making a killing by
buying rice, selling it on the
futures market.
You understand, this is riskless.
If I sign a contract to
sell rice in Chicago on the
futures market, that is riskless.
And so, why don't I just do that?
I think that there must
be some, in some level, there
must be some storage.
There must be some storage cost problem.
In order to actually do this,
you'd have to buy the rice and
store it for six months.
And I'm thinking that that must
explain, it must be that at
this point in time, storage
costs are, in some sense, too
high for this to be a real profit opportunity.
So, this is what happens now in the real world.
There are people who store rice.
There has to be, right?
Because rice.
There's no one harvest, because there's different
kinds, but there's no more than
a few harvests in the year.
Some of them are bigger than others.
And so, it's got to be stored.
And this really, really matters, because if it's not
stored, some people are going to starve to death.
So, it really matters.
And you have professional warehouse operators who, they
sure do know what this curve says.
And they're thinking, right now, I'm sure lots of people
looked at this curve yesterday,
and they thought, look at that
contango.
Wow.
This is a lot of contango.
And they're thinking, well, I'm going
to see if I can get some
other warehouse.
Can I get another?
There's an empty building on the south side of Chicago.
Maybe I can fill it up with rice.
And so, I have to look up,
and I have to get inspections and
sanitation checks.
And think about insurance.
And they're thinking about that.
But they find out that it's
not going to work, and they're
trying.
This generates.
When you have a lot of contango in
the market, it generates a lot of contango.
And it generates enthusiastic efforts by smart
people to try to store more rice.
And you see what that's doing.
It's helping prevent a famine.
Now, this goes back to, I know I'm putting
it in dramatic terms, but this goes back to
Adam Smith, who in his Wealth of Nations in
1776 has a famous passage, which I can't quote
exactly, but it was something to the effect
that, you know, there's a lot of people who
express benevolent impulses.
You know, they give to charity.
They talk about, they go to church
regularly, and they talk about love thy neighbor.
But they're not doing a single
thing to prevent the next famine.
They're not thinking about it.
The people who are really effective are these quiet
guys dealing in the markets, and they see a
contango, and they see something coming.
And so, they get in the business of storing.
And it's purely out of self-interest.
So, the famous quote that is quoted a million
times from Adam Smith, and it's, you know, it's a
quote that's been quoted a million times.
It's a quote that's been quoted
a million times from Adam Smith.
It's, these people operating in their own
self-interest seem to be more important in
promoting human welfare than
all the benevolent people combined.
I'm quoting him roughly.
Well, there has to be
an element of truth to this.
You know, people who do these storage
of grains do not get much respect.
And at dinner conversations, nobody cares what they do.
They're really good at what they do.
And so, the market.
But they quite, and you
know, they're not saints either, right?
They're speculators.
They're trying to make a profit.
Now, one thing I wanted to say
about futures also, which I didn't really clear.
In forward markets, which are markets
between a pair of counterparties, there's always
counterparty risk.
I'll write that.
That means you've got a contract.
You had a lawyer.
A lawyer wrote up the terms.
You can take this guy to bankruptcy court
or something, but that's all a nuisance and
it costs money.
You never know.
Futures markets get rid of counterparty
risk, or essentially get rid of it.
And how do they do that?
The system is one of, it's a
standardized retail market that anyone can buy.
It's a standardized retail market that anyone can play in.
But you have to post margin.
And that's the idea.
Margin.
When you either buy or sell futures.
Okay, so this is what happened.
This is what a futures contract looks like.
You can do this.
I don't know what would happen if
you called up a broker at your age.
Essentially, you can do this.
I know Jeremy Siegel, my friend said, he
would actually lend money to students and let them
play the markets.
His own money.
I have never done that, so
don't ask me to do that.
But you can basically call up a
broker and say, I'm interested in rice futures.
It sounds like fun to me.
I'd like to play that game.
So, the broker would say, fine.
I'll open a margin account.
How much money are you going to put in?
All right.
So, you have to put in some money.
The first question is money.
Okay?
He doesn't know who you are.
But money talks.
Okay?
So, you say, all right, you have to
come up with some money to do this.
Let's say, I'll put in $5,000
into a futures account at your brokerage.
And he would then say, okay, now you have $5,000.
And the margin requirement for rice futures, I
don't remember what it is, say it's something
like 3% or 5%.
And then you have to go up
to the limits imposed by your margin.
Your margin has to be whatever
percent of the contract that you sign.
Okay?
And then I'll let you put, you know,
you can buy, you're only putting up $5,000.
I'll let you buy and sell $100,000 worth of rice.
So, this is what happens.
You say, okay, I want to
buy, what do I want to do?
I'm going to store rice and
then I want to sell it.
So, I want to sell futures.
And then I'm going to put up money.
Now, I'm going to sell it.
So, I'm going to put up money.
So, I'm going to sell it.
Either way, you've got to put up money now.
So, let's say, I'm going
to do this rice storage business.
So, I've got my own, I can do it.
It's open to anybody in the world.
I can find a warehouse, I can buy some rice, I
can store it, and I can sell it at that price.
So, I want to sell futures, okay?
I can sell $100,000, even though
I've only got $5,000 put up.
I don't have to put up
money because I'm going to buy it.
So, let's see, I'm going to
keep it on a regular basis.
Okay, now, if I sell futures,
I'm going to get a $1,000 contract.
If I sell futures on a
regular basis, I'm going to get $1,500.
And then I'm going to put up money.
Okay, if I sell futures on a regular
basis, I'm going to get a $1,000 contract.
Now, the futures price is the price on that
contract today, but it's not a price you pay today.
Okay, but now the futures
price today is the price that
the market has today.
Tomorrow the futures price will be different.
And so, what they have
in the futures markets is daily
settlement.
And that means that if I
sold futures, as I'm storing rice
and selling futures, if the price goes down, the price
goes up, it works against
me, because I've locked in the
lower price.
So, the broker debits my margin account.
Every day they change my margin account.
So, if I've sold futures and
the price goes up, they take
it out of my margin account.
If the price goes down, they
put it into my margin account.
And I can quickly deplete my $5,000.
Suppose price keeps going up.
Then I say, gee, I wish I hadn't.
I'm sorry.
I'm sorry I didn't sign
that contract, because I could have
waited a few days and gotten a better price.
Meanwhile, the broker calls you
on the phone and says, I'm
sorry, your margin account is almost depleted.
Do you want to put up more margin?
And this is where you
get the reality of futures trading.
Because there's no counterparty risk.
That means that if you don't
put up more margin, the broker
closes you out, and says, here's your money.
Do you understand how this works now?
Because it doesn't matter whether you're a drunk or a
sociopath, the broker has you trading, and it doesn't matter
at all what you do.
Once you put up the money,
and if you just don't answer the
phone, if you say you
don't answer the phone, the broker
will close you out when the margin is depleted.
So the broker takes no risk.
The counterparty is not even given to you.
You don't even know who's
on the other side of that
contract, because the other side is making a, you're both
making a contract with the exchange.
And so, you don't care about counterparty risk, and there's
no risk to this contract.
That means these prices are pure prices, and they don't
have any counterparty risk.
I have another.
I wanted to show you another.
This is a futures contract.
This is soft red winter wheat,
which is a major crop in the
U.S. Winter wheat you plant in the fall.
Believe it or not, some
people are surprised to hear this.
You plant it in the fall,
and then it stays in the ground
over all the winter, and it
comes up really early in the
spring.
And then it's harvested.
And it's harvested.
And the last thing I
want to talk about is the
future.
This is, for example, early summer.
Okay?
And the soft red winter wheat
is very good for biscuits, and
cold cereal, and cakes, but not so good for bread.
So, it's a particular kind of wheat that is grown.
So this is the futures
curve as of Friday for this.
And this is in cents per bushel.
So, this is the front month futures.
And it looks like it's $7.23 a bushel.
And now we see the sharp contango again.
And the prices are going up really rapidly through time.
Again, this is all prices quoted last Friday.
This is futures contracts of different maturities.
And then you see, sometime
around summer of 2012, it loses.
It loses contango, right?
And it becomes actually declining.
And then this market goes out to 2013 and stops.
That's as far out as they trade futures.
So, why is it declining in 2012?
Well, there's probably a million factors.
And you'd need to talk to a futures expert.
But I think one thing that
comes to my mind is the harvest.
Right?
And so, they harvest grain.
And you know, you shouldn't
be storing grain at the harvest.
This contango is a compensation for the cost of storage.
So, you shouldn't be storing grain in the harvest time.
You should be clearing out your warehouses
and sweeping them out and cleaning them up
and waiting for the new harvest to come in.
So, you don't expect contango to continue then.
There's a seasonal.
And you know, you can't just wait.
You can't wait.
You can't wait until the harvest is seasonal.
It's not so clear here.
It's not dropping very much.
I don't know.
There's many factors that determine these prices.
But I wanted to just give a
little bit of simple mathematics about futures pricing.
And then,
the basic formula is that you have
to think of futures markets as storage markets.
And the basic equation is that the price in a futures contract,
P sub f is the futures price on one of those dates,
is equal to 1 plus r.
Right?
So, 1 plus r plus s times the spot price.
Okay?
Where the spot price, P sub
s, well, I'll write it out.
P spot is the price today.
Okay?
Now, this is kind of theoretical because I've just told
you nobody ever knows what the price today is anyway.
Because the only way you ever
know prices is through futures market.
But let's just think a little bit abstractly.
Say there's a cash market for wheat.
And there's a market for wheat
that it's bought and sold with.
And we know what the price is on that market.
So, this is the interest rate between now.
It's not the annual interest rate.
It's the total interest as a percent
between now and the maturity of the contract.
Okay?
So, if it's one year and the
interest rate is 5%, then r is 0.05.
But if it's a year, then r is 0.05.
But if it's one and a half
years, it's going to be more like 0.075.
Right?
Because the total interest between now and one
and a half years in the future is 7.5%.
And s is the storage cost.
Okay.
So, this is called fair value.
And what it means is, normally, you
think futures prices should behave like that.
Okay?
All right.
So, the normal situation in futures markets
is contango, which means that prices are normally
going up through time because the longer in
the future we're looking at, the longer time
that we're losing interest and storage.
See, what this really is, this fair value
equation, is just the expression of the value
of the future.
It's just the equation that defines when it
is that there's just no profit to storing
grain.
Right?
There's only a normal profit, right?
People who do it, this equation can't hold
exactly, or if it held exactly, then no one
would store grain.
But it has to be approximately valuable.
Okay?
So, do you see, so how else to say this?
It shows that normally the futures
price is above the spot price.
And as time goes on, and I don't mean
time in this sense, I mean calendar time, the
futures price will converge on the spot
price because the interest rate, the horizon for
the interest rate and the
storage cost, this is in percent.
And this is in percent.
It goes down.
So, let me just clarify that.
Let's talk about a perfect world where there's no profit.
It's a perfect world where there's no harvest uncertainty.
Nothing happens except the crop is normally produced.
Okay?
And it's wheat.
And let's say, I'm going to do a plot.
And this is time.
This is calendar time, not
maturity time like on this plot.
And this is the price of this.
I'm going to plot, well, I'm
going to plot this price of wheat.
So, what does wheat do over the year?
I'm going to say seasonal.
I'm going to do an abstract form of seasonal.
This is what the price of wheat does.
And this is a year.
This is year one.
This is year two.
This is year three.
Year four.
All right?
This is the price of
wheat in each of these years.
It falls every harvest time, right?
It has to be rising until harvest because
somebody has to be storing grain and the price
of wheat is rising.
And then, it falls again
because they're facing storage costs.
And then, every spring, every harvest time, it collapses.
Then, it does it again every year.
No uncertainty.
What do futures prices do?
Well, let's consider a futures market that's
a futures contract that has a maturity right
here at the peak, just before the harvest.
Okay?
Well, if there were no uncertainty, the
futures price would just be constant throughout that
time, right?
It would always equal the expected
spot price on that future date.
And again, it would repeat the next year.
So, I'm looking at futures contracts.
Futures contracts have no expected
price change in this perfect world.
And do you see what I'm saying?
This equation always holds because as this contract
matures, the time to the end of the
expiration date goes down.
And so, this r goes down and s goes down.
And it eventually hits zero on the expiration date.
And the futures price equals the
spot price on the expiration date.
But in reality, we don't see
such a nice and perfect match.
I want to talk about another futures
market, which is maybe the most important futures
market at all.
I've been talking just about agricultural futures.
Okay?
So, I'm going to talk about the futures market.
Agricultural futures are the origins of futures markets.
And I like to talk about them because
I like to imagine, well, our ancestors all lived
on farms once in the past.
And it just seems like such a family
story that we all should know about farming, right?
It's our history.
But now, let's move forward into other –
we can have futures markets for oil as well.
So, let's talk about the futures market.
So, let's talk about Friday's futures
curve for light sweet crude oil.
This used to be NYMEX, New York
Mercantile Exchange, but the Chicago Mercantile Exchange
has been buying everybody up.
And now, it's the CME –
they call it the CME Group, actually.
Chicago Mercantile Exchange Group.
And this is the price of oil.
Look what's happening here.
Isn't this something?
This curve.
The price of oil as of last Friday.
And this month's futures was selling at $101 a barrel.
It's gone up a lot.
This is part of the crisis now around the world.
People need food and they need oil.
Incidentally, the two markets are related because we
can turn fuel – we can create fuel from
food by using grains to produce
ethanol and that substitutes for oil.
So, it's not independent.
These two markets are not independent.
Now, oil is so important.
It's the energy that drives the world economy.
And any events, like the recent earthquake
in Japan and the nuclear disaster in Japan,
it affects this market.
Everyone is thinking, what does it mean for oil?
Maybe we won't have so many nuclear plants anymore, so
that's going to mean oil is going to go up.
People are thinking it.
What they're thinking is – the other thing
that's happening is, at this point in history,
there's a crisis in the Middle East
and it's cutting off the flow of oil.
So, people are trying to protect oil.
So, people are trying to predict it.
And those predictions come into this market.
So, here's what we see.
We see, right now, the market
is predicting increases of oil until December.
And then, a collapse of oil prices.
Bottoming out in January of 2015.
This market goes all the way out to almost 2020.
That's a long time.
That's because it's such an important commodity.
So, this futures curve matters for – the total value of
oil in the ground in the world is probably over $100 trillion.
It's bigger than the GDP of just about any country.
It's huge and important.
And people who are thinking of extracting their oil,
they're looking at – everyone's looking at this curve.
So, why does it peak in
December of 2011 and then collapse?
I'm guessing that has something to do
with the crisis in the Middle East.
The people who trade these markets are thinking that the crisis
will be over by then and prices will start coming down.
So, we're seeing contango here and backwardation here.
I'm using a simple definition of contango and backwardation.
There's more subtle definitions, but we'll keep it simple.
We're seeing an increase expected in
oil prices and then a decrease.
And then, it's going to go.
It has it going up again.
Is this right?
Well, if it isn't right,
there's a profit opportunity for you.
If you know better, you can get in and you can
do it with, I think, all you need is something like $5,000.
I'm not trying to entice you to trade this, but I'm just
– I'm trying to give the idea of what these markets really mean.
That these are – that the
oil, it means survival for people.
I mean, oil and food are
what keeps people going and alive.
And there's not enough.
There's not enough for everybody.
And so, this market is all about extracting oil at a good rate, thinking about
when to sell it, so that it ultimately, I think, serves the purpose of humanity.
Now, incidentally, what about what's happening here?
You see the curve falling, okay?
How can that be?
I just –
I just wrote this equation here, saying that the futures price
has to equal 1 plus r plus s times the spot price.
So, the futures price has to
be greater than the spot price.
I just wrote that, right?
But you can see that this futures
price, this is essentially the spot price.
This is the front month future.
And it's about to expire, so it's converging.
And this is what we call the price of oil.
When you hear oil prices
quoted on TV or in magazines,
they're quoting the front month futures.
Let me be clear about that.
Oil is mostly sold on long-term contracts.
So, just like our rice merchant.
Buyers of oil are typically –
who buys crude oil?
It's some refinery, right?
And they've got a big operation, and they refine oil.
And they care about, what
kind of oil do I get?
And when is it going to be delivered?
And what are you going to do
for me if it's not delivered on time?
And they have complicated delivery contracts.
Almost all oil is sold through that.
So, what is the price of oil?
You can't figure it out.
There's just too many contracts, and they're all different.
There is a spot market for oil.
But that's just overflow.
You know what happens?
There'll be some mistake.
Someone delivered too much oil to the New Haven Harbor.
And it's not – or someone reneged on a contract.
Now, I've got this extra oil.
It goes on to the spot market.
But that market is tiny and just not reliable.
You don't know what kind of oil it was.
It's all different of what the issues are.
So, when you hear oil prices, you're hearing futures prices.
So, what's happening?
How can it be that the futures price
in 2015 is lower than the price today?
Well, there is something funny going on.
I'll tell you one thing
that it does mean to me.
It means that nobody is planning
to store oil between now and 2015.
Right?
Because – at least not as a storage business.
Because I'm going to lose money.
I'm going to be selling at less
– unless I had negative storage costs.
I'm not going to store oil between now and then.
I'll store it for now.
So, that means that people are kind of trying to
store a lot of it now, because the contango is there.
And then, it's going to end in December.
And then, they're going to empty their storage tanks.
That must be what storers are thinking.
So, this thing doesn't always hold.
This only holds when there's commodity in storage.
Or you could say, well, it
still holds even when you have backwardation.
Because in some sense, storage costs can get negative.
Okay?
So, let me just talk about – there's
a term that they use called convenience yield.
When the futures curve is in backwardation,
somebody is still going to be storing oil.
Right?
So, suppose I have a factory.
And my factory depends on oil, because I
use it to burn, to produce whatever we make.
Am I going to let my warehouse,
my storage tank of oil, go dry?
No.
I'm going to need some, just because
we might need more than we think.
We might have a buffer stock.
So, that means I actually have negative storage costs.
I always want oil.
I don't want ever to let my tanks go dry.
So, the only people who are storing
oil, when you have a backwardated futures market,
are the people who want convenience yield.
Now, I'm omitting some subtleties here.
I'm sorry, but I'm trying to make the
basic point, that this equation holds when the commodity
underlying is in storage, but it doesn't always hold.
Okay.
So, now I wanted to talk about oil
a little bit more, because it's so important.
I have here the price of oil.
I like history.
I like to give you long history.
I wanted to give you the price of oil.
So, let's go back to 1871.
And this is, well, U.S. oil price in U.S. dollars.
But I've corrected for inflation, so it's real oil prices
from 1871 until just a short while ago, last week.
Yes.
So, this is the price of oil.
Now, in recent years, this
is the front month oil contract.
The oil futures market started in the 1970s.
So, this is all the front month futures contract.
Before that, this is someone's guess as to what the
price of oil was, because there weren't such well-developed markets.
We didn't have oil futures until the 1970s.
So, I wanted to show you this.
So, I wanted to think about
what was happening at these various dates.
These early swings in the 1870s were due to
discoveries of oil and discoveries of uses for oil.
Pennsylvania oil was discovered somewhere around
this time in the United States.
Texas oil was discovered somewhere around
And oil was so dependent on petroleum.
Actually, if you look up oil on ProQuest back in
1870, they didn't even call it oil, they called it petroleum.
And it wasn't so, because what was oil?
What did they think oil was in 1870?
Whale oil.
Okay, it was a different world.
So, we see a lot
of jumping around of oil prices.
But there was.
You see a big surge going into the 1890s.
And there was a big scandal about Standard Oil.
Remember that?
And the government eventually busted
up Standard Oil as a monopoly.
So, they were starting to get concerned about oil.
But then, if you go forward in
time, you see this interesting pattern here.
What was going on here?
The price of oil became very stable.
Until, bang!
There was this huge upswing in oil.
Well, what was happening in this interval of time, in the
40s to 60s, the U.S. was a big producer of oil.
It kind of got started here, oil
production, with Drake's invention of the oil rig.
And the U.S. was the biggest producer of oil.
And during this period, when you
see oil prices were very stable.
The oil prices were actually stabilized by
the, it was produced mostly in Texas.
Texas Railroad Commission.
It says railroad, but it was a government agency in
the state of Texas, which worked to stabilize oil prices.
So, during this period of time,
the U.S. was depleting its oil.
And other oil discoveries were coming in.
And so, this whole period, this
is before there were any futures markets.
Because there was no reason for a futures market.
Oil prices were very stable.
And then, you see here, a
sudden jump up in oil prices.
And this point right here
is called the first oil crisis.
And so, the first oil crisis.
It kind of stands out on the diagram, right?
Looking at the whole history.
If you exclude those early fluctuations in oil that you
see in the 1870s, which were not really so important,
because people weren't really so dependent on oil.
But by, so the first oil crisis was 1973, 74.
And this prompted the creation of the futures market.
Because what happened was, it was actually
coincided with the Yom Kippur War in Israel.
And it was created by a
blockade against oil in oil producing countries.
The U.S. was no longer, by
this time, the major producer of oil.
We had something called OPEC.
Which is the Organization of Petroleum Exporting Countries.
It actually goes back to 1961 with Qatar.
1962, Libya, Indonesia.
And then, we added the Abu Dhabi in 67.
The United Arab Emirates, 74.
Algeria in 1969.
Nigeria in 1971.
Ecuador in 1973.
Gabon in 1975.
So, what happened was, although the U.S. broke the Standard
Oil monopoly in the, around the turn of the century,
a new monopoly developed.
And it was outside the U.S.
And so, there was no
trust busters to break this monopoly.
And so, what happened was, the
oil exporting countries who belonged to OPEC,
who wanted to use oil prices
as a strategy to deal with Israel,
they restricted their supply of oil.
And it caused the first oil crisis right here.
I was going to mention another historical fact.
I think it's,
I think it's a little bit more complicated than that.
But it's part of the story.
And that is,
nationalizations of oil.
It used to be that big oil companies
went around the world and found oil deposits.
And they would buy the land, and
they wouldn't tell anybody what they were doing.
They would buy the land that was
owned, that had the oil under it.
So, the oil companies were very rich.
But there was discontent in the less developed countries,
who sold them the land and thought,
why did we get gypped like that?
And so, they started a process.
It started with Mexico in 1938.
So, oil used to be,
owned by the oil companies.
Mexico said,
no, not any longer.
It's our national heritage.
We never should have sold it to you.
We're just taking it back.
This was considered outrageous at the time.
No country should violate property rights like that.
But it was kind of a leftist,
the word nationalization was a new word.
It was kind of like the people expressing their heritage.
So, it started to take.
Then Iran in 1951.
And then other countries followed.
So, oil got taken away from international companies
and put under government
control of less developed countries.
And then there was a monopoly called OPEC.
And that produced this crisis right here.
There was a second oil crisis in 1979, 80.
And it was a crisis
that was not just about oil.
And this one, again, was associated
with trouble in the Middle East.
So, in 1979, 80,
we had the Iranian Revolution,
which again disrupted oil supply.
So, 1979, 80 is the second oil crisis.
And that is due to the
fall of the Shah of Iran
and the arrival of the Ayatollah Khomeini
and the Iran-Iraq War.
And so, you can see
the huge increase in oil prices.
These were real panic situations at the time,
because people were not used to these,
people were used to the stable oil price.
And it was just something taken for granted.
But this put the world in a state of shock,
because oil price really jumped up almost sixfold,
about sixfold in a matter
of, how many years is that?
Six, seven years.
So, this left a lot of
interest and enthusiasm for oil futures.
And it became a major market
of the kind we know about today.
You know what happened here, this market?
This is another, this is the second Iraq War,
when Saddam Hussein was,
when the Persian Gulf was overthrown.
And U.S. and other countries were involved in that.
But what it did is, it
cut off the supply of oil briefly,
because the Persian Gulf was
shut down because of a war.
You can bet that the futures
market was heavily backwardated right then,
for oil, because oil, everyone knew
that the oil prices were not temper,
we weren't running out of oil,
we were just, we couldn't get
at it because of the war.
So, this was another oil-induced spike.
Every one of these spikes
produced a major worldwide recession,
because the world wasn't ready for these spikes in oil.
So, we see this huge spike in oil in 73,
in a worldwide recession.
Again, another worldwide recession.
This one was called the Great Recession.
People forgot that they called it that,
and used that term again more recently.
And then there was another worldwide recession.
Every one of these did it.
And so, you can see the fundamental importance of oil,
and of oil futures, because
oil futures is managing the risk.
If you bought an oil futures contract,
you didn't, you weren't impacted by this.
If you bought a contract just before this,
then I don't, you know, the
oil prices doesn't mean anything to me.
It's not my problem, because
I've already locked in my price.
And it's really safe, because
the way the futures markets work,
they've got this daily settlement process.
You don't have to worry about your counterparty reneging.
It's very civilized.
It's a tough world out there, where they're fighting wars.
But in Chicago, where the futures markets are,
or it was New York back
then, it's a very civilized market.
And so, look here, we have the latest spike.
It's even bigger.
So, oil got to, I can't even reach up there.
Oil got up to over $140 a barrel in 2008.
That's just a short time ago.
Now, what did that?
That is kind of a puzzle.
It has something to do with the world financial crisis.
But it's not as well understood
as a reaction to any military situation.
So, it seems like there's some speculative element
that took place.
See, ultimately, oil is stored in the ground,
and it's owned by people.
And they have to decide how to develop it,
and how fast to produce it and sell it.
And there were some quick changes of thinking around then
that surprised everyone, I think.
And oil is again up
above $100 a barrel right now,
just as we saw on the futures curve.
So, actually, the futures curve,
that we saw, would look kind
of unimpressive on this diagram, right?
It would be just going up
a little more and a little down.
Not big swings that are predicted.
So, I think that, let me just say one,
I just want to finally conclude with financial futures,
which I didn't emphasize in this lecture.
But we also have futures.
And we have futures markets in financial commodities.
And I'm just going to
tell you about one of them.
It's called the S&P 500 futures market, index futures.
And now, in effect, you have to
deliver not oil or rice or wheat,
but you have to deliver the S&P 500 index.
Which, how do you do that, by the way?
How do I deliver 500 stocks?
Well, there's a procedure, and it's called cash settlement.
It's different.
Instead of showing up at a
warehouse with your trucks full of wheat,
you only show up with the money.
And so, because they don't expect
you to do that with stocks.
The other thing about, what
is the storage cost for stocks?
Well, you know, it's actually negative.
It doesn't cost me anything to buy.
If I buy a share in a
company and store it, it doesn't cost me.
It's a negative cost, because they pay a dividend.
So, the fair value, and this is
what you'll see quoted all the time
on CNBC or any of these
business, Bloomberg or these business networks,
is, so the futures price is equal to
R minus Y times the spot price.
Same formula.
This is the interest rate.
And this is the dividend yield.
Okay?
So, now, whether the futures price
is above or below the spot price
is less clear here.
Because it depends on whether the interest rate
is higher than the dividend rate or lower.
At this point in history, for short time horizons,
the interest rate is less than the dividend rate.
We have about a 2% dividend yield on stocks.
And we have essentially a 0% interest rate.
So, for short horizons, we'd expect to see
the futures price less than the spot price
in stock index futures.
But at longer horizons, I think that would be reversed.
But this market is very clear.
The fair value relationship is
highly predictive of futures prices
in the S&P 500 index futures,
because there's always storage of stocks.
We never deplete the warehouses of stocks.
So, they're always there.
And so, that means that the
futures curve is less interesting for stocks
than it is for oil.
All it does is reflect fair value.
And so, it's not like oil, where
you can't see the stock market.
It's not like oil, where
The storage situation is very
complicated, and it's constantly changing.
So, in a sense, the S&P 500 index
futures is not so much about the future.
The futures curve is not so much
about the future of the stock market.
So, don't make the mistake of looking
at the futures curve for the S&P 500,
because you can't see the future of the stock market,
because you haven't seen this curve.
You can't.
Basically, the S&P 500 is very hard to forecast,
and the futures curve doesn't do you anything,
because all it reflects is fair value.
So, some futures markets, like
gold futures is like this also.
There's always gold in storage, never gets depleted to zero.
It's always being stored.
So, the gold futures curve is not so interesting, either.
So, after the midterm exam, which
you have coming up on Wednesday,
we will come to options pricing.
And that's another fascinating market that we'll talk about.